Guide to the George and Evelyn Harper Collection
University of Kansas
George and Evelyn Harper papers
1933-1987
University of Kansas Kenneth Spencer Research Library Kansas Collection 1450 Poplar Lane, Lawrence, KS 66045-7616 Phone: (785)864-4334 Fax: (785)864-5803 URL: http://spencer.lib.ku.edu
Harper, George, 1918-2004
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
The papers of George and Evelyn Harper are those of a native Kansan couple. George Harper served as Atchison, Kansas' first African American mayor and Evelyn Harper became a leader in education.
RH MS 671
RH MS-P 671
BIOGRAPHY of George and Evelyn Harper
George Harper was born in 1918 in Atchison, Kansas. After attending Atchison public schools (Lincoln School and Atchison High School), Harper attended St. Benedict's College. He then worked as a superintendent at Kerriford Quarries in Nebraska and Missouri as well as a maintenance mechanic at the Rockwell Transportation and Equipment Division. There he served as president of the Local Union 6934 of the United Steel Workers of America. While working as a mechanic, Harper was also a City Commissioner; he was first elected in 1973, becoming the city's first African American City Commissioner. He was reelected in 1975 and 1977. In 1979, Harper became Atchison's first African American mayor. He served in that position until his retirement in 1981.
Harper was active in the community, serving on the advisory council for the Atchison Community Development Corporation and as a member of the Atchison Co. Committee for Correction Reform and the Atchison Recreation Commission. He was also an active member of Ebenezer Baptist Church.
On 12 June 1947, George married Evelyn R. Wofford. Evelyn Wofford was born 15 June 1913 in Kansas City, Kansas to Hence and Laura Wofford. After attending schools in Oklahoma and Wisconsin, Evelyn attended New York University, where she received her Bachelor of Science degree. She received her Master of Arts in Sociology from Columbia University and her Education Specialist Degree from the University of Kansas. In 1937, Evelyn began work at Oklahoma's Langston University and, six years later, she became an elementary and junior high school principal. Upon returning to Kansas, Evelyn worked as an Executive Secretary at Kerford Quarry before continuing her work in school's in 1947. At that time she became principal at Lincoln School (Atchison), where she worked until 1955, when she became a reading teacher at Atchison High School. In 1973, she became the School's Associate Principal and, in 1976, she became Principal of Atchison Junior High. She held that position until her retirement in 1983. She was recognized for her work in education with several awards, including the Kansas Teacher of the Year (1966) and the Master Teacher Award (1966).
Evelyn was very active in various organizations, acting as President for a number of them, including the Les Dames Literary Club, Alpha Kappa Alpha, the Kansas State Teacher's Association, the Kansas Council of the International Reading Association, the Atchison branch of the American Association of University Women, and the Kansas branch of the National Education Association. She also was a charter member and president of the Topeka Chapter of Links, Inc. She also served as Vice Area Director and Area Director for the Central Area of that group.
Evelyn Harper died 23 May 1992 in Atchison. George Harper follwed her on 19 March 2004.
SCOPE and CONTENTS
The Papers of George and Evelyn Harper date from 1933 to 1987 and are divided into two series: George Harper and Evelyn Harper. George Harper's papers consist mainly of photocopies of two scrapbooks kept by Harper; items include clippings, certificates, and awards. Evelyn Harper's papers are divided into three subseries: Career Papers, Organizations, and Personal Papers. Career Papers include correspondence, clippings, and items from her various professional positions. Organizations include correspondence, clippings, and conference information. Personal Papers include correspondence, clippings, and educational information. Folders within each series and subseries are arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
Photographs from the George and Evelyn Harper Collection are located at RH MS-P 671.
RELATED MATERIAL
Harper, Evelyn W.
Planning a teacher's handbook for a developmental reading program. Thesis (M.A.Ed.), University of Kansas, Education, 1963.At Thesis 1963 Harper, Evelyn, Anschutz Library and as Thesis 1963 Harper, Evelyn, Annex 2.
Series List
The Papers of George and Evelyn Harper date from 1933 to 1987 and are arranged in two series and three subseries.
George Harper, 1957-1987
Evelyn Harper, 1933-1982
Subseries: Career Papers, Organizations, and Personal Papers.
INDEX TERMS
Names:
Harper, George, 1918-2004.; Harper, Evelyn W., 1913-1992.
Organizations:
Links, Inc.
Subjects:
African American mayors -- Kansas -- Atchison.; Atchison (Kan.) -- Politics and government.; African American educators - Kansas.; University of Kansas. School of Education -- Alumni and alumnae.
Acquisition Information
Gift, Evelyn Harper, 1988.
Loan, George Harper, 1988.
Gift, George Harper, 1993.
Restrictions on Access
No access restrictions.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
- RH MS 671
- George Harper, 1957-1987
  - (Box Box 1)
    - Clipping, 1977 (Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Folder 2)
    - Correspondence -- to George and Evelyn Harper, 1957, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook no. 1, 1973-1981 (Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook no. 2, 1967-1987 (Folder 5)
- Evelyn Harper, 1933-1982
    - Career Papers, 1947-1982
    - Atchison Junior High -- Clippings, 1975, 1977, 1979-1982 (Folder 6)
    - Atchison Junior High -- Misc., 1976-1977, 1979 (Folder 7)
    - Atchison Public Schools -- Misc., 1961, 1970, 1978, 1980-1982 (Folder 8)
    - Correspondence -- Incoming, 1955, 1964, 1966, 1968-1971, 1975, 1980-1982 (Folder 9)
    - Correspondence -- Outgoing, 1968, 1970, 1975, 1978 (Folder 10)
    - Curriculum Vitae, 1988 (Folder 11)
    - Lincoln School -- The Lincoln Star, 1947-1950 (Folder 12)
    - Lincoln School -- The Lincoln Star, 1951 (Folder 13)
    - Lincoln School -- Misc., 1949 (Folder 14)
    - Misc., 1951, 1966, 1968 (Folder 15)
    - Misc. clippings, 1965-1966, 1970-1974 (Folder 16)
    - Organizations, 1942-1982
    - Alpha Kappa Alpha, c1942, 1966, 1979 (Folder 17)
    - American Association of University Women, 1954, 1966, 1968-1971 (Folder 18)
    - Atchison City Teacher's Association, 1970 (Folder 19)
    - Heroines of Jericho, 1961, 1963 (Folder 20)
    - International Reading Association, 1967-1968, 1971-1973 (Folder 21)
    - Kansas-National Education Association/National Education Association -- Clippings, 1966, 1970, 1974, 1976; Folders 22-26 are labeled "K-NEA/NEA". (Folder 22)
    - K-NEA/NEA -- Correspondence, 1966, 1970-1972, 1975-1976, 1978-1979, 1982 (Folder 23)
    - K-NEA/NEA -- The Kansas Teacher, 1970 (Jan, Mar, Apr, Sept), 1971 (Jan) (Folder 24)
    - K-NEA/NEA -- Legislative Committee misc., 1974 (Folder 25)
    - K-NEA/NEA -- Misc., 1971, 1975-1976, 1982 (Folder 26)
    - Kansas State Teachers Association -- Clippings, 1963-1964, 1969, 1970 (Folder 27)
    - Kansas State Teachers Association -- Correspondence, 1964, 1969-1971 (Folder 28)
    - Kansas State Teachers Association -- Election materials, nd (Folder 29)
    - Kansas State Teachers Association -- Misc., 1969 (Folder 30)
    - Les Dames Literaire, 1954, 1958 (Folder 31)
    - Links -- Assembly Info. -- Central Area, 1967-1970 (Folder 32)
    - Links -- Assembly Info. -- Central Area, 1971; Respectively, folders contain: Agendas and programs, Registration forms, and Reports. (Folder 33-35)
    - Links -- Assembly Info. -- Central Area, 1972 (Folder 36)
    - Links -- Assembly Info. -- General, 1968 (Folder 37)
    - Links -- Assembly Info. -- General, 1970 (Folder 38)
    - Links -- Central Area Chapter president's list, 1968, 1970 (Folder 39)
    - Links -- Central Area Chapter Report questionnaires, 1965, 1968 (Folder 40)
    - Links -- Central Area Chapter Report questionnaires, 1969 (Folder 41)
    - Links -- Central Area Chapter Report questionnaires, 1971 (Folder 42)
    - Links -- Citation Certificate, 1965 (Folder 43)
    - Links -- Clippings, 1964, 1968-1970 (Folder 44)
    - Links -- Constitution and by-laws, 1966 (Folder 45)
    - Links -- Correspondence -- Incoming, 1967-Feb 1971 (Folder 46)
    - Links -- Correspondence -- Incoming, Mar 1971-1972 (Folder 47)
    - Links -- Correspondence -- Outgoing, 1968 (Folder 48)
    - Links -- Debutante info., 1964, 1967-1968, 1970 (Folder 49)
    - Links -- Fine Arts info., 1970-1971 (Folder 50)
    - Links -- History of the Central Area Links, 1987 (Folder 51)
    - Links -- Membership lists/directory, 1970 (Folder 52)
    - Links -- Misc., 1968, 1971-1972 (Folder 53)
    - Links -- Misc. chapter reports, 1968 (Folder 54)
    - Links -- Misc. meeting info., 1968, 1970 (Folder 55)
    - Links -- National Vice President campaign materials, 1972 (Folder 56)
    - Links -- Publications -- Area newsletters, 1965, 1970-1971 (Folder 57)
    - Links -- Publications -- The Links Journal, 1966, 1968 (Folder 58)
    - Links -- Questionnaires, n.d. (Folder 59-60)
  - (Box Box 2)
    - Links -- Report -- "Links in Area Conferences,", 1971 (Folder 1)
    - Links -- Report -- "Link Women in Action: the Area of Trends and Services (National and International), a Brief History of the Program Emphasis on Trends and Services and Handbook," (Folder 2)
    - Links -- Topeka Chapter info., 1971 (Folder 3)
    - Misc., 1948, 1971, 1976 (Folder 4)
    - NAACP, 1947, 1970 (Folder 5)
    - Personal Papers, 1933-1982
    - Correspondence, 1965-1966, 1970, 1976-1977 (Folder 6)
    - Misc., 1968, 1980-1981 (Folder 7)
    - Misc. clippings, 1937, 1943, 1968, 1970-1971, 1979, 1982 (Folder 8)
    - Misc. programs, 1966-1967, 1971-1972, 1982 (Folder 9)
    - New York University commencement program, 1933 (Folder 10)
- Photographs, RH MS-P 671
  - (Box Box 1)
    - George Harper, n.d. (Folder 1)
    - George Harper -- Kerford Quarry Baseball Team, Atchison, KS, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Evelyn Harper, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - Evelyn Harper -- at Atchison Junior High School benefit basketball game, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Evelyn Harper -- with Atchison Junior High School students, c1977; One print with two partial enlargements (Folder 5)
    - Evelyn Harper -- in Classroom with students [Atchison Grade School, 1960s?] (Folder 6)
    - Evelyn Harper -- Kansas Area Links and husbands (Folder 7)
    - Evelyn Harper -- Links Christmas Party snapshots, 1970 (Folder 8)
    - Evelyn Harper -- Links conference in the Bahamas, 1964 (Folder 9)
    - Evelyn Harper -- with Lincoln School students, n.d. (Folder 10)
    - Evelyn Harper -- Kerford Quarry snapshots, n.d. (Folder 11)
    - Evelyn Harper -- Snapshots of misc. students, n.d.; Most are identified on the photo's backs (Folder 12)
    - Evelyn Harper -- with unidentified men, n.d.; Negative (Folder 13)
    - James Hayes Parks, Jr., n.d.; Son of Topeka Link Julietta Parks;he is a classical singer. (Folder 14)
    - Unidentified women at "Atchison World Community Day,", n.d. (Folder 15)